Register of the David Starr Jordan Papers, 1794-1950
Hoover Institution Archives
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1873-1932
  - Wichman, E. K., 1915 (Folder 43)
  - Wiers, Edgar S., 1914 (Folder 44)
  - Wilbur, Curtis D., 1924 (Folder 45)
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1910-1929 (Folder 46)
  - Wilcox, Delos F., 1914 (Box 83, Folder 1)
  - Wilder, Burt G., 1882-1883 (Folder 2)
  - Wildman, Edward E., 1916 (Folder 3)
  - Wildman, M. A., 1912 (Folder 4)
  - Wilkins, James H., 1913 (Folder 5)
  - Wilkinson, Charles, 1915 (Folder 6)
  - Williams, Frank F., 1914 (Folder 7)
  - Williams, John Sharp, 1919-1922 (Folder 8)
  - Williams, M. Ida, 1915-1920 (Folder 9)
  - Williams, Wardner, 1914 (Folder 10)
  - Willis, Bailey, 1915 (Folder 11)
  - Willis, F. Milton, 1910 (Folder 12)
  - Willis, Frank B., 1922 (Folder 13)
  - Wilson, A. M., 1915 (Folder 14)
  - Wilson, C. L., 1910 (Folder 15)
  - Wilson, Huntington, 1910-1914 (Folder 16)
  - Wilson, John, 1914 (Folder 17)
  - Wilson, William J., 1913 (Folder 18)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1912-1920 (Folder 19-20)
  - Winslow, Erving, 1913-1918 (Folder 21)
  - Wirt, Lincoln, 1929-1930 (Folder 22)
  - Wisconsin Peace Society, 1917 (Folder 23)
  - Wisconsin Teachers' Association, 1911 (Folder 24)
  - Wise, Stephen S., 1916-1920 (Folder 25)
  - Woehlke, Walter V., 1915-1923 (Folder 26)
  - Wolf, Georg, 1913 (Folder 27)
  - Wolfe, A. R., 1911 (Folder 28)
  - Woman's Peace Party, 1916 (Folder 29)
  - Woman's Republic, 1914 (Folder 30)
  - Women's Committee for World Disarmament, 1921 (Folder 31)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1922-1931 (Folder 32)
  - Wood, L. Hollingsworth, 1915-1921 (Folder 33)
  - Wood, Leonard, 1917 (Folder 34)
  - Wood, S. T., 1913 (Folder 35)
  - Wood, Thomas D., 1915 (Folder 36)
  - Woodhull, Maxwell, 1915 (Folder 37)
  - Woodward, A. Smith, 1913 (Folder 38)
  - Woodward, Frederic C., 1916 (Folder 39)
  - Woodward, Henry H., 1914 (Folder 40)
  - Woodward, W. A., 1928 (Folder 41)
  - Woolley, C. W., 1919 (Folder 42)
  - Work, Hubert, 1923-1925 (Folder 43)
  - Workers' Defense Union, 1921-1923 (Folder 44)
  - Works, John B., 1915 (Folder 45)
  - Works, John D., 1917 (Folder 46)
  - World, 1897-1913 (Folder 47)
  - World Peace Association, 1918 (Folder 48)
  - World Peace Foundation, 1911-1929 (Box 84, Folder 1)
  - World Unity, 1928-1930 (Folder 2)
  - World Unity Foundation, 1928-1929 (Folder 3)
  - World's Court League, 1917 (Folder 4)
  - World's Work, 1912-1915 (Folder 5)
  - Wright, M. H., 1914 (Folder 6)
  - Wright, May, 1914 (Folder 7)
  - Wrong, George M., 1911 (Folder 8)
  - Wythe, J. H., 1918-1919 (Folder 9)
  - Yale News, 1914 (Folder 10)
  - Yamawaki, H., 1916 (Folder 11)
  - Yates, M. M., 1913 (Folder 12)
  - Young, Morgan, 1923-1929 (Folder 13)
  - Young, Robert, 1913-1923 (Folder 14)
  - Young Men's Christian Associations, 1911-1928 (Folder 15)
  - Young Women's Christian Associations, 1916-1921 (Folder 16)
  - Yoximovich, C., 1923-1924 (Folder 17)
  - Zellers, M. T., 1914 (Folder 18)
  - Zimdars, J. B., 1918-1919 (Folder 19)
  - Zinsser, Hans, 1914-1924 (Folder 20)
  - Zirkel, Adolf, 1914 (Folder 21)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1872-1929
  - Titled works
    - Bibliographies of the writings of David Starr Jordan. 2 printed copies, entitled For International Peace, Stanford University, 1925. 5 copies with the same title, dated 192 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - "Above All Nations," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 2)
    - "Above All Nations Is Humanity," 5 copies (1 handwritten, 1 typewritten, 3 carbons) (Folder 3)
    - "After Nine Years," 1915. 1 carbon copy (Folder 4)
    - "After the War," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 5)
    - "After War - What?" n.d. 1 copy (typewritten and handwritten) (Folder 6)
    - "Aim of the War," December, 1917. Boston Post. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 printed) (Folder 7)
    - "Albania," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 8)
    - "Alsace-Lorraine," n.d. Handwritten notes and drafts, typewritten drafts (Folder 9)
    - "Alsace-Lorraine Since 1914," n.d. 3 copies (1 handwritten, 1 draft, 1 carbon) (Folder 10)
    - "Ambitions of Pangermany," synopsis of a speech at Stanford University, June 6, 1918. 3 copies (1 handwritten, 1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 11)
    - "American Graduates in Japan," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 12)
    - "American Peace Prize," n.d. 2 copies (1 carbon, 1 printed) (Folder 13)
    - "Annexation and Conquest," Scientific Monthly, May, 1916. 3 copies (2 drafts, 1 printed) (Folder 14)
    - "Answer to the Attorney General of California," June, 1923. 3 printed copies (Folder 15)
    - "Anti-Alien Agitation in California," 1913. 1 carbon copy (Folder 16)
    - "Appeal for Cooperation Towards Lasting Peace," March 21, 1916. 14 copies (1 draft, 13 printed) (Folder 17)
    - "Appeal to American Patriotism," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 18)
    - "Argument for War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 19)
    - "Arguments for the War System," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 20)
    - "Armament, Victory and Peace," Jan. 31, 1915. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 printed) (Folder 21)
    - "As to Mexico," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 22)
    - "As to Prophecy," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 23)
    - "As War Begins," extracts from a letter written in London, August 12, 1914. 1 carbon copy (Folder 24)
    - "Assisting the Enemy," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 25)
    - "Australian Defence and Its Relation to International Peace," May, 1914. 1 carbon copy (Folder 26)
    - Autobiography, an extract entitled "Dr. Charles J. Albert," n.d. 2 carbon copies (Folder 27)
    - "Balance of Power," n.d. 1 printed copy (Folder 28)
    - "Balkan Brew," n.d. 1 printed copy with handwritten notes (Folder 29)
    - "Balkan Tragedy, The," reprint from the Journal of Race Development, October, 1918. 3 printed copies (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - "Balkans, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 carbon, 1 handwritten) (Folder 2)
    - "Belgium," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 3)
    - "Belgium," co-authored with Raymond Macdonald Alden, October 9, 1915. 1 printed copy (Folder 4)
    - "Bernhardi in San Francisco," n.d. 3 copies (2 typewritten, 1 carbon). One copy entitled "General Friedrich von Bernhardi" (Folder 5)
    - "Blind Man's Holiday," 1899. Typewritten and carbon pages from Imperial Democracy: A Study of the Relation of Government by the People, Equality Before the Law, and Other Tenets of Democracy, to the Demand of a Vigorous Foreign Policy and Other Demands of Imperial Dominion, New York, D. Appleton and Company, 1899 (Folder 6)
    - "Bogoslofs, The," co-authored with George Archibald Clark, reprint from the Popular Science Monthly, December, 1906. 1 printed copy (Folder 7)
    - "Bok Peace Award, The," n.d. 3 printed copies (Folder 8)
    - "Bok Peace Plans," n.d. 3 printed copies (Folder 9)
    - "Britain's Preparedness," n.d. 1 typewritten and handwritten draft (Folder 10)
    - "Builders of Democracy," n.d. 2 copies (handwritten and typewritten drafts) (Folder 11)
    - "California and the Japanese Problem," The Christian Work, March 24, 1923. 2 printed copies (Folder 12)
    - "Call of the Red Cross, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 13)
    - "Can Germany Pay?" San Francisco Bulletin, September 15, 1923. 3 printed copies (Folder 14)
    - "Captain Sleeps, The," April 26, 1899. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 15)
    - "Capture of Private Property at Sea, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 16)
    - "Case Against War, The," The Daily Journal and Tribune, Knoxville, Tennessee, August 4, 1912; August 11, 1912. 2 copies (1 carbon, 1 printed) (Folder 17)
    - "Cash Cost of War, The," April 25, 1915. 3 copies (1 carbon, 1 handwritten, 1 printed) (Folder 18)
    - "Ce que l'Amérique peut enseigner à l'Europe," extrait de La vie internationale, 1913. 2 printed copies (Folder 19)
    - "Certain Items as to the Assumed 'Japanese Menace,'" n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 20)
    - "Christ and the War God," San Francisco Bulletin, December 15, 1923. 4 copies (3 printed, 1 carbon) (Folder 21)
    - "Christmas Message, A," December, 1913. 1 printed copy (Folder 22)
    - "Christmas Word, A," Concord, December, 1913. 1 printed copy (Folder 23)
    - "Citizenship in a Democracy," n.d. Speech notes (?). 1 typewritten copy (Folder 24)
    - "Collapse of Insurance, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 25)
    - "Colonial Expansion," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 26)
    - "Community of States, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 27)
    - "Concerning Sea Power," World Peace Foundation, Pamphlet Series, January, 1912. 1 printed copy (Folder 28)
    - "Concerning War Debt," April, 1917. 1 carbon copy (Folder 29)
    - "Conduct of Modern War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 30)
    - "Confession of Faith, A," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 31)
    - "Co-Operation and the League of Nations," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 32)
    - "Costs of War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 33)
    - "Crime of the Century, The," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 34)
    - "Crisis in Germany, The," October 31, 1923. 3 copies (2 printed, 1 carbon) (Folder 35)
    - "Cry of Agony, A," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 36)
    - "Czecho-Slovaks, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 37)
    - "Damage of War, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 typewritten) (Folder 38)
    - "Day of Liberation, The," speech on Armistice Day, Richmond, California, n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 39)
    - "Days of a Man," extract. 1923. 1 carbon copy (Folder 40)
    - "Dealing with War Debts," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 41)
    - "Defense of Democracy, The," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 42)
    - "Demands of the Navy League, The," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 43)
    - "Democracy and Freedom," n.d. Printed galleys (Folder 44)
    - Democracy and World Relations, advertising and excerpts from publication, 1918. Review in German (Folder 45)
    - "Democracy Has Not Failed," n.d. 4 printed copies (Folder 46)
    - "Disarm Pacific, Insure Peace," October 18, 1921. 1 printed copy (Folder 47)
    - "Discipline, Dynastic or Democratic," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - "Dr. Dernburg and German Victory," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 2)
    - "Does Human Nature Change?" n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 3)
    - "Dry War and Red," n.d. 7 copies (1 handwritten, 2 typewritten, 3 carbons, 1 incomplete draft) (Folder 4)
    - "Dynastic Diplomacy," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 5)
    - "Dynastic State in History, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy, handwritten notes (Folder 6)
    - "Education for Peace," Journal of Education, December 18, 1924. 3 printed copies (Folder 7)
    - "Emotions and Foreign Policy in America," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 8)
    - "End of the War, The," n.d. 4 copies (1 typewritten, 3 carbon) (Folder 9)
    - "Enduring Peace," Sunset, n.d. 3 printed copies (Folder 10)
    - "Ernst Sieper," n.d. 1 typewritten and handwritten draft (Folder 11)
    - "Eugenics and War," rebuttal by Jordan to charge made against this article, 1918(?) 5 copies (2 typewritten, 3 carbon) (Folder 12)
    - "Europe's Hunger for Peace," n.d. 3 copies (1 typewritten, 2 carbons) (Folder 13)
    - "Europe's Opinion of Bulgaria," abstract of speech in Sofia, Bulgaria, March, 1914. 3 copies (1 typewritten, 2 carbons) (Folder 14)
    - "Failure of the Western Campaign, The," January 11, 1916. 1 carbon copy (Folder 15)
    - "Fallacy of Privilege, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy. (Folder 16)
    - "Far West of Islam, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 17)
    - "Farce and Tragedy of Loyalty, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 18)
    - "Farmer and the Recent Strikes, The," New Republic, October 25, 1922. 1 printed copy (Folder 19)
    - "Farmer and War, The," Farm and Fireside, December 5, 1914. 6 copies (1 printed, 1 typewritten, 4 carbons) (Folder 20)
    - "Federation," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 21)
    - "Federation of Europe, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 22)
    - "Fifteen Thousand Ways to World Peace," Los Angeles Times, August 16, 1925. 1 printed copy (Folder 23)
    - "First Cost of War, The," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 24)
    - "Fishes Found in Japanese Waters," n.d. 4 printed copies (Folder 25)
    - "For Durable Peace," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 26)
    - "Freedom in Wartime," The Public, May 4, 1918. 9 printed copies, 1 wrapped package of printed copies (Folder 27)
    - "Friede, Der," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 28)
    - "From Feudalism to Centralism," 1872. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 29)
    - "From World Understanding to World Peace," November, 1929. Introduction. 1 carbon copy (Folder 30)
    - "Fruits of Victory, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 31)
    - "Future of Alsace-Lorraine, The," reprint from The Journal of Race Development, July, 1918. 2 printed copies (Folder 32)
    - "Generic Names of the Surgeon Fishes and Their Relatives, The," n.d. 1 carbon draft (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - "German Militants in Foreign Lands," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 typewritten) (Folder 2)
    - "German Propaganda in Foreign Lands," n.d. 1 carbon copy, 1 draft (Folder 3)
    - "German Propaganda in the U.S.," n.d. 1 printed copy (Folder 4)
    - "Germany Since 1918-19," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 5)
    - "Germany's Future," November 2, 1923. 2 printed copies (Folder 6)
    - "Glory of War, The," November 10, 1923. 2 printed copies (Folder 7)
    - "Governmental Obstacles to Insurance," reprinted from The Scientific Monthly, January, 1916. 2 printed copies (Folder 8)
    - "Great Pacific War, The," n.d. 2 carbon copies (Folder 9)
    - "Great War of Europe, The," n.d. 3 copies (1 typewritten, 2 carbon copies) (Folder 10)
    - "Great War, The: What Shall We Say in the Schools?" n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 11)
    - "Grimmest Failure in History, The," n.d. 1 mimeographed copy (Folder 12)
    - "Guarantee of Peace, The," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 13)
    - "Guerre et la virilité, La," La paix par le droit, January, 1911. 2 printed copies (Folder 14)
    - "Handwriting of War Still on the Wall," San Francisco Chronicle, January 9, 1927. 1 printed copy (Folder 15)
    - "Henry Ford and the Peace Crusade," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 16)
    - "Herbert Clark Hoover: An Appreciation," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 17)
    - "Higher Culture," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 18)
    - "Higher Patriotism and the College Man," speech at the University of Pennsylvania, November 19, 1915. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 19)
    - "History Repeats Itself," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon (Folder 20)
    - "Hope for Peace, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 21)
    - "House, Edward Mondell," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 22)
    - "If War Should Come," n.d. 3 copies (1 mimeographed, 1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 23)
    - "Ills of British Democracy, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 24)
    - "In Memory of the Mikado of Japan," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 25)
    - "In Search of Truth," reprint from The Popular Science Monthly, February, 1907. 1 printed copy (Folder 26)
    - "In Submergence of Democracy," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 27)
    - "In Terms of War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 28)
    - "In the Triumph of Peace," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 29)
    - "In the Wilderness," Phi Beta Kapa Poem, 1913. 2 printed copies (Folder 30)
    - "Indictment of War, An," September, 1913. 1 carbon copy (Folder 31)
    - "Individual and the State, The," n.d. 2 carbon copies (Folder 32)
    - "Innate Righteousness of War, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 33)
    - "International Law," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 34)
    - "Interview on Leaving Japan," October 12, 1911. 1 carbon copy (Folder 35)
    - Interview with David Starr Jordan, Seattle Union Record, April 16, 17, 1918. 1 printed copy (Folder 36)
    - Introduction to an article by Dr. Otto Seeck entitled "The Stupendous Folly of England's War Policy," November 25, 1914. 1 printed copy (Folder 37)
    - "Is the War System a Permanence?" n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 38)
    - "Isolation Plan, The," reprint from the University of California Chronicle, January, 1922. 6 printed copies (Folder 39)
    - "It Pays for a Nation To Be a Gentleman," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 40)
    - "Japan," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 41)
    - "Japan and China," April 28, 1915. 3 copies (2 carbon, 1 handwritten) (Folder 42)
    - "Japan and the Society of Nations," March, 1919 (?) 3 copies (1 handwritten and typewritten draft, 1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 43)
    - "Japan and the United States," n.d. 3 copies (2 carbons, 1 handwritten) (Folder 44)
    - "Japan and World Relations," May, 1924. 8 copies (1 carbon, 7 printed) (Folder 45)
    - "Japan in California," Boston Evening Transcript, December 29, 1906. 1 printed copy (Folder 46)
    - "Japan in 1922," n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 47)
    - "Japan, 1911," n.d. 1 typewritten draft (Folder 48)
    - "Japanese Problems, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - "Jingo Talk," n.d. 4 carbon copies (Folder 2)
    - "John Casper Branner," reprint from Science, March 31, 1922. 1 printed copy (Folder 3)
    - "Joint Commissions of Inquiry and Conciliation," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 4)
    - "Jones," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 5)
    - "Jordan Outlines Plans for New Deal in Europe," Standford Palo Alto News, September 14, 1917. 1 printed copy (Folder 6)
    - "Jordan Warns Against Unnecessary Bonding," The Daily News, San Francisco, California, May 22, 1922. 1 printed copy (Folder 7)
    - "Joshua Knew About it," Colliers, January 3, 1925. 3 printed copies (Folder 8)
    - "Kaiser," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 9)
    - "Kakichi Mitsukuri," n.d. 2 copies (1 mimeographed, 1 carbon) (Folder 10)
    - "Krieg und Mannheit," Internationale Verstaendigung, 1912. 5 copies (1 typewritten, 1 mimeographed, 1 draft, 2 printed copies), 1 partial draft (Folder 11)
    - "Land of the Sleepless Watchdog, The," Unpopular Review, July, 1914. 2 copies (1 typewriten, 1 carbon), 1 extract of the article (Folder 12)
    - "Last Cost of War, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 13)
    - "Law of War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 14)
    - "League of Nations, The," May, 1919. 16 copies (15 printed, 1 handwritten) (Folder 15)
    - "League of Nations and the Treaty of Peace, The," n.d. 3 copies (2 handwritten, 1 typewritten) (Folder 16)
    - "Legion of War Makers, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 17)
    - "Lesson from Lincoln, A," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 18)
    - "Lessons from the Transvaal," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 19)
    - "Let Hatred Die in the U.S.," n.d. 2 printed copies (Folder 20)
    - "Letter to a Friend in Switzerland," September, 1918. 3 copies (2 carbons, 1 handwritten and typewritten draft) (Folder 21)
    - "Letter to a German Democrat in Switzerland, A," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 22)
    - Letters to the editor
      - Unidentified, n.d. 1 printed copy (Folder 23)
      - Argonaut, June 18, 1911. 1 printed copy (Folder 24)
      - Boston Post, July, 1917. 1 carbon copy (Folder 25)
      - Chicago Daily News, n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 26)
      - Chicago Tribune, April 23, 1915. 2 carbon copies (Folder 27)
      - Eugenics Review, n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 28)
      - Facts, June 21, 1917. 1 photocopy (Folder 29)
      - Freeman, February 16, 1922. 1 carbon copy. March 16, 1922. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 30)
      - New Republic, September 25, 1917. 1 carbon copy (Folder 31)
      - New York Call, n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 32)
      - New York Globe, August 9, 1920. 2 copies (1 carbon, 1 handwritten) (Folder 33)
      - New York Times, April 11, 1915. 1 printed copy; December 14, 1917. 1 carbon copy; April 1, 1917. 1 carbon copy; 3 handwritten undated letters (Folder 34)
      - Palo Alto Times, n.d. 2 printed copies (Folder 35)
      - St. Louis Republic, February 27, 1915. 1 printed copy; March 17, 1915. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 typewritten) (Folder 36)
      - San Francisco Bulletin, April 10, 1917. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 37)
      - San Francisco Chronicle, n.d. 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 38)
      - Toronto World, n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 39)
    - "Letter to the Members of the Class of 1873 of Cornell University, A," November 8, 1918. 1 printed copy (Folder 40)
    - Letters at the Democratic Convention, July, 1920. Printed copies and carbons of the newspaper columns (Folder 41)
    - "Liberation of Macedonia, The," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 42)
    - "Lodge and the League," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 43)
    - "Long Cost of War, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 44)
    - "Madness of War, The," n.d. 2 carbon copies (Folder 45)
    - "Magdalena Bay Again," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 46)
    - "Makers of War, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 47)
    - "Manual of Vertebrates," n.d. 3 printed copies (Folder 48)
    - "Martinet and the Conscientious Objector, The," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 49)
    - "Meaning of Democracy, The," n.d. 1 mimeographed copy of speech notes (?) (Folder 50)
    - "Meaning of Pacificism, The," January, 1921. 1 copy in the Japanese Student Association magazine. 1 copy in The Stanford Sequoia, n.d. (Folder 51)
    - "Meaning of the War, The," September, 1914. 2 copies (1 draft, 1 typewritten) (Folder 52)
    - "Menace of Militarism, The," April 16, 1915. 3 copies (1 carbon, 1 handwritten draft, 1 printed) (Box 47, Folder 1)
    - "Methods of Medieval Warfare," n.d. 1 incomplete carbon copy (Folder 2)
    - "Mexico Next," n.d. 13 printed copies (Folder 3)
    - "Militarism in the Schools," n.d. 2 copies (1 draft, 1 carbon) (Folder 4)
    - "Military Expert on International Affairs," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 5)
    - "Military Position of the United States," n.d. 1 printed copy (Folder 6)
    - "Military Training in American High Schools," February 5, 1916. 4 copies (1 typewritten, 2 carbon, 1 printed) (Folder 7)
    - "Minimum of Safety, The," n.d. 3 copies (1 draft, 1 carbon, 1 handwritten) (Folder 8)
    - "Miocene Shore Fishes of California, The," reprint from The Scientific Monthly, November, 1921. 1 printed copy (Folder 9)
    - "Modern Warfare," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 10)
    - "Moisson Humaine, La," 1911. 2 printed copies (Folder 11)
    - "Month of Terror: August, 1914, The," August 31, 1914. 3 copies (1 draft, 1 typewritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 12)
    - "Moral Equivalent of War, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 13)
    - "More About the Ruhr," n.d. 2 printed copies (Folder 14)
    - "Mussolini: The Outgrowth of Instability," n.d. 2 printed copies (Folder 15)
    - "Mysterious Stranger, The," n.d. 1 carbon copy (Folder 16)
    - "Nation in Arms, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 17)
    - "National Defense," n.d. 1 printed copy (Folder 18)
    - "Nationalism and War," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 19)
    - "Nationality of Saloon-Keepers," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 20)
    - "Naval Waste," February, 1913. 4 printed copies (Folder 21)
    - "Need in Palestine, The," n.d. 2 copies (1 handwritten, 1 carbon) (Folder 22)
    - "Neuroses of Hate Stirred World to War," n.d. 4 copies (2 printed, 2 carbons) (Folder 23)
    - "New Argument for War, A," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 24)
    - "New Morality, The," n.d. 1 handwritten copy (Folder 25)
    - "New Year Is Promising for Peace," Palo Alto Times, January 1, 1926. 1 printed copy (Folder 26)
    - "No 'Higher Duty' for the United States," July 30, 1915. 1 printed copy (Folder 27)
    - "No War on the Pacific," n.d. 3 printed copies (Folder 28)
    - "Nobel Prize Winner," The Survey, January 18, 1919. 2 printed copies (Folder 29)
    - "Not More Ships but Fewer Entanglements," n.d. 2 carbon copies (Folder 30)
    - "Not Strictly Accurate," n.d. 1 draft (Folder 31)
    - "Notes from the Balkans," n.d. 1 typewritten copy (Folder 32)
    - Notes, notebooks